A referee is Ben O'Keefe from New Zealand, touch judges, Matthew Rannell, James Dolman,
Brendan Pickwell is a TV match official. Number one in the world, Ireland take on the defending
champion South Africa. It's a Poobee match which could easily be as tight as a facelift.
Welcome to start the France straight away. It's Damian Villainsa into the fray. He's
upended. South Africa in their white jersey. Their third strip at this rugby will come.
Bafta Clark looking to go wide early on and it's been spilt on that far side by Ches and
Colby.
Ambitious from South Africa straight off the start. The kick from Milan coming straight
down the middle. I think Bafta Clark just a little bit of extra nervous energy in that
pass, probably overcooked a little bit. Normally so efficient getting out of this part of the
field South Africa. Look at this for a statement off the opening chase. Thumbs off. It's Kelleher
gets, what a technique in the tackle. Drives Villainsa back. We've got a little bit of
an early issue for Josh Vandevleur here. He's getting a bit of treatment.
Chakiya Haba, head coach, took the role in 2020. Needs his position after this World
Cup to replace Stuart Lancaster as Leinster's head coach. Andy Farrell there since 2016
as an assistant but head coach since 2019.
And he's 33 out of 40 tests him and that is an outstanding record. He's going very smartly
indeed. But this the biggest test of all, Rugby World Cup.
This crowd is absolutely electric. I'll tell you what, Ireland's warm up song today was
Smoke on the Water by Deep Purple. But in this stadium at the moment it is a sea of
green. They were expecting around 30,000 Irish fans to come to start to France today. But
it certainly sounds like more. It is absolutely incredible.
The pitch side, Necky Nidhi's undone, Stanford Road, Olympia time, Mitchell pinch at the
line of time for South Africa. He comes away though for Ireland. Down the right they go.
Gibson Park shifts it. Fords looking for some work around the fringes. Ty Burr. Such an
experienced player, puts his head down, does the Monster Man. Gibson Park yet again to
the left. That's a Gary Ringrose. Cuts in nicely into the 22. It's Ireland now that
are building their phases nicely early on. Burn again for the second carry. Sexton finds
his full back. Hugo Keenan. Such a cunning player with advantage to the Irish side now.
Burlong turns it to Vande Aki. He's 50th international for his country. Ireland go to the right.
That's a big pass. A lot of time. Number one, he just came on the wrong side and rolled
into number nine. Will stay with Ireland. An early look at that Ireland attack. The
deception at play is quite fantastic. Already we've seen those passes fizzed across the
front of players. As a defender it looks like they're going to receive it and then it goes
to the next man. Keeping on their rock speed as well. Ireland's rock speed so far. Fastest
in the tournament. Less than three seconds per rock. And they are here to play. Sexton
will pop this one in the corner. Jimmy, good space, good sit up. Make sure we've got the
two by two for the nine. One of the 7,000 Irish bars around the globe. Certainly enjoying
this endeavour from the Irish side. How many? 20 tries in the opening two matches. Four
middle. More passes in those two games than they did in the whole of the last Rugby World
Cup. To the front they go. Ty Burne can't pinch. And it's hoofed downfield by Colby.
Not out. Left behind from Matt Hanson. Always going backwards in the touch. Happy to see
Jimmy. And so Ireland go quickly. F*** the clock. Spots a bit of space. And it's an awkward
bounce but it's good for South Africa. Courtney Aronson has it. Look out. Creel's on the
inside. Big Jesse Creel into the 22. And the clean up from Dlndi. Through the legs it
goes. Seven style play there from F*** the clock. Game back on Jasper Visser. South Africa
now. Their chance to attack. Big step. Daniel Villamse. Does well inside the 22. The ball
is now for the spring box. The clock. Works the short side to his captain. See how Colisey.
Got the penalty. Blungie in the Nandis. Big carry from the hooker. Visser again for the
second time. Ireland's wall holding strong. Here comes Yvonne Etzebeth. Man that's built
like a Bulgarian vending machine. To the right it goes again. Creel trying to skip through.
Not back to Peter Step Detoi. And it will be a penalty for South Africa. What an entertaining
opening. Four minutes. Dream straight over the top off feet to me. You know a shot there
Detoi. We just saw he's getting some treatment on the ground now. He got hit a little bit
late. Yeah I think James Ryan went straight through him there. And the eyes up to the
coaching box to see what kind of traffic lights are flashing on. Shots called. Two metres.
There's the ambition from South Africa. It's a pretty loose kick but the bounce did Aronson
a favour. We're Ronaners. He dished it back inside to Creel who was supporting. Ringrose
with the scramble tackle and nearly on the pinch. We didn't see anything. He was furious
wasn't it. From South Africa and there's a little look at bit of afters. So there we
go. Area which they've struggled in this rugby world cup. Ten out of eighteen kicks. They've
got the ball. It's a big part of winning rugby world cup matches. So the fly off from the
players. South Africa's first shot at goal. Maniloboc turns the flags go up. South Africa
have the opening points in this game. They lead on and three nothing off the five. There's
the
infringement. Nice one for Maniloboc to settle himself in. He's been backed by both coach
and captain in terms of his kicking. He's only on forty percent kicking. That's a nice one
to get off the board. Sexton down the middle. Franco Mustard is there. Places rugby with
the heat in Japan. Can't use it. Fifth gift cap against Scotland during this rugby world
cup. Six season with the spring box. He goes to the air. Colby comes down a bunch of green
jerseys. Hanson does really well. Does the right wing up for Ireland. They have it at
the halfway line. Jamison Gibson Park. There's Scrum off. One of eleven. The starting side.
Very familiar with their teammate Sexton. Tries to get it away. Flies in. Penalty on
it. No attempt to catch the ball. He's just hit that on the short pass. Apparently only
players outside. It's a really fascinating little tactical battle. Ireland playing with
that flat attack. Sexton taking it right close to the line and against the line speed of
South Africa. It's a real challenge. See he just holds his feet, stands still to try and
play around the line speed. After Clark absolutely flies off the line, doesn't he? Such an
acceleration as they scum off. And now it's Ronan Kelleher. Again they've had a trouble
at line up time. Two knock ons. First ball and let the line out. Sexton South Africa.
South Africa Scrum. Two loose ones. Thought the battle at Scrum and line up would be
fascinating tonight. I actually thought it would be an area where Ireland might get a bit of
change. James Ryan will be making the calls in there. First Scrum, stability at the bind.
Good weight at the sit. Balance. Lost one at the front. It was Dutoy getting up for South
Africa earlier on. Great speed and that one looked like it was just an overthrow. When you're
trying to throw it between jumpers like Etzabeth and Dutoy and the likes of them, you've got to
be on your money. Many intriguing match ups we've seen. Scrum time. 34 scrums this year
coming into this tournament. Battle 34 but they lost one of their own against Romania and one
against Scotland. Arlen, you pulled it back, you went early. Next one's a penalty. Wait for
my call. Three kick to the spring blocks. Another scrum. We all came in early, OK? Wait for the
call. I'm waiting for stability. Then I'll call set. I'll be louder. I will. Next one's a penalty.
Wait for the timing of the call. Kitsuff wants to go again. I'd say Furlough wouldn't mind a bit
of that. They'll look to right or wrong in this one. Take two. Coach! Boins! Set! Keep it up now!
Chesman-Colby lurking behind Faf de Klaag at scrum time. Visser picks up. Blashes his way upfield.
Here, here, here. De Klaag looks for Peter Steph Dutoy. St. Abagas rugby player of the year three times.
OK, use it! Box one high again. Another excellent take of an absolutely eaten on the ground is Mack Hanson.
Arlen. You're fine. You're on the wrong side. You've got to roll quicker if I want a reward too. You're OK.
It's just fours on the wrong side. Nice explain by Van O'Keef. The jackal is a bongi on Benambi on the
jackal, which was legit. I was really happy with that contest. I thought he was off your arm. I thought your
elbow was up as well. But it was even at Stibeth just lying on the wrong side. Deemed to be creating a
hurdle for the clearers. What about that scrum? The Irish forwards reckon that they took great confidence from
that win against South Africa back in November. Even a couple of the backs have attended the scrum sessions this week.
So some education in the dark arts. Of course, South Africa poses such a physical challenge, but they're also
technically smart. So this is going to be a huge challenge for Ireland.
Yeah, now they're in their look on. Some of the extras. Eleven players from Ireland. Eleven from South Africa who played in that
last game. Well here tonight. 1960 was a score there. Ireland winning by three. Traditionally been very close
encounters over the top. The fourth line up goes the right for Andy Farrell side. A worrying point for them so far in this game.
Franco Mustard is at the back there. De Klaak for the touch line this time. Nice clearance from the scrum off.
Yes, lovely techers from Fafter Klaak there. He managed to get his side up towards the 10 from that position. He's admirable.
Real concern for this Ireland line up though. And perhaps South Africa won't mind pumping the ball at the sideline.
He's seen five. Continue to put threat. They're going to go for a five man line out. See if they can get it right this time.
Pressure on Kelleher. 25 year old. He's 24th cap for Ireland. Can he find his mark? Yes is the answer. Pidoh Mani with a great take in his 100th
appearance. And now flat ball in the middle from Sexton. Changes direction. Ringrose throws a dummy.
The carry with James Ryan. Players play out of the air for Ireland in 2019. Khaleesi a real nuisance around the breakdown.
Sexton, nice dummy. Couple of fakes and they go over the top. Here comes Ireland now. Beautiful bit of work. Keenan. The fox gets very close.
Does Hugo Keenan. Akira is in there as well. Kelleher to the right. Here come the Irish now. Cailan Doris. They get very very close.
That's off the back of a fabulous sequence of attack. They managed to get the line out right this time. And then they were off and running.
What about the throw over the top. The pump. And then that perfectly played ball. It's Keenan. Would defend the pirouette and oh so close.
Guys time's a lot. Let's go please. Speaking to Andy Farrell pre-match. Even he wasn't sure if they were going to be able to play that attacking attractive rugby that they have played in the first two games.
Given the physicality of South African side. But it's pretty clear the intent is there already as we see Andre Pallard there.
He's going to come back into the South African squad officially as a replacement for Malcolm Marks.
Good hide this side. Great audio there from the crowd as you said. Andre Pallard. Amazing addition for the Africa side.
Kick 22 points to the Rugby World Cup final in 2019 against England.
We'll cover from his car. Penalty South Africa. It's scrum time.
It's gone again twice. It's now a penalty. Wait for my call please.
Thanks boys.
Another early engagement identification from referee Ben Akeed. I don't think there's a problem when they're down scrumaging. At the moment it's just the process.
Obviously not quite O.F.A. with Mr. O'Keefe's calls or something. But I need you to be able to adapt to the call. It's slow. I'm waiting for balance and then you can go.
I saw Green come first. Please adapt. Thank you.
Often it's because they're so desperate to meet the hit against the strong scrumaging side. They don't want to lose that initial hit. But at the moment they're going early.
South Africa get their line with Etzebeth in the front. Khaleesi now in midfield with courageous captain. Tackle. Got his knee on the ground. Tackle.
Good. Turnovers good. Being pinched. Up the middle come Ireland. Tight burn. And then Ireland lose it. Did well to stop South African captain.
Good. Turnovers good. Tackle. Got his knee on the ground. Tackle. Did you get a turnover? Did you get a good turnover? Knock on.
We'll give it to you. It's a crisp seed from LeVoq to his skipper. Talk to Ronan timing. He was met pretty smartly by Kalan Doris. They try and do the hold up. Eventually it ends up being a ruck.
He gets the steal and it's the offload from Doris. I think he might have dropped one close to the line. He's shelled another. It was good defensive work. They'll be encouraged by that. Turnover first phase.
The bomb squad seven and one split on the bench. So much chat about that of course since they use it against New Zealand in the warm ups.
He's eating at a premium on that bench with seven forwards taking up all the space. Kovac-Rynapp the only lucky back to make the cut. But I love it, Dalton, because I think it reminds us that rugby is about the skill set.
It's not just the number on your back. I think that's a useful thing to remind youngsters of. You know, don't think too much about the position you're playing. It's as much just what you bring to the game. You bring that wherever you play.
Yeah, you're right. Some opposition fans question the decision. Some say I could support us all. But as nervous as a long-tailed cat in a room filled with rocking chairs. But it worked for them in the past.
Innovation. It's good for the game. Breaking the mould as we've seen the South Africa team do before. It's creative. We'll see how it goes over the course of this game.
Jacques Nineber admit that there was an element of risk to picking a 7-1 split on the bench. But there was an element of risk in everything in rugby. You could get a red card early so it was a risk they were willing to take.
Yeah, you're so right. That's true. Nineber and the brain stress of this spring box who of course won the last one in 2019. Played in seven of the nine rugby world cups.
Up the clack comes to Willemsep. Played fly off as well early in this tournament. Damien Willemsep does really well. Both full backs having some strong feet. Here comes the giant frame of Etzabeth that takes his shot as well to the ground.
The clack. Want a quicker ball for Livock to attack with. Here comes Umbanami. Wide ball from Pfaff. Finds Adesap. Good tackle low gets in as well. It's Ireland that's stopped this attack and draw the penalty as well.
What a ball.
I always think back three players get particularly fired up when they get turnover. James does really good over the ball. He's also got an absolutely monster boot on him.
He's pretty smart with ball in hand as well.
Such a weapon for this Irish side.
The defence has been good.
The opening 16 or so minutes of this game.
Let's work hard on the step here. Met you everyone at the front.
Okay, Sam, you've got a receiver. Two metres.
Willemsep will get his naughty feet out. There's the turnover. Manages to get a hand on the ball. Look at that.
Supporting his own weight. Nice and low. Great technique.
So here we go.
Can Ronan Kelleher
Andrew, come down.
Continue to get line of possession here.
Okay. What's that Met you?
It's an Irish side that have won 27 of 29 games in the last two years. Only losing to New Zealand and France.
Sit up off the mark. Off the mark.
Managed to work a five man line up earlier with a bit of movement and that was the key.
That's good now.
Again, it's moving. This time they come right to the front.
Secure ball. Kelleher rips it away.
Aki, steaming in.
What a bulldozer he is for the Irish side. But it's South Africa.
That are all over this one as well.
Both sides winning breakdown penalties.
Seven's on the good side. Nine, careful. You've got the penalty.
Here it is.
Side, drop the ball.
The little raff on the wrist for Fafta Clark for rubbing it in.
Expect nothing less from the nine.
I'm definitely watching.
Don't get involved. You've got the penalty.
Yeah, I agree.
So Bandi Aki coming on that hard line.
I mean he has been ridiculous so far. They've had two fairly comfortable games.
But in those games he's gone for about 268 metres.
Marked the line. On and off.
I think he's been praised by anyone who's had him in their fantasy team.
Because he's been scoring points wholesale in that.
He's a player you do not look past.
Sexton also collecting a ton of points for the Irish side last time.
Le Book finds Aronson. Flat ball. Jesse Krill comes flying in.
The Clark again. Nice ball on the inside. Peter Steff, the toy.
And it's the spring box now.
They find themselves on the front foot.
No, no, no!
And Benavi and Exibeth in there as well.
Between the legs. Le Book.
Behind the bat to Diolendi. Puts one to the ground.
And the inside set up. He's a bulky frame as well.
The hands down the chain.
A kick through from Damian Villamse.
And he has timed that to perfection.
No. It was OK.
Real celebration.
The perfect kick. Just staying the right side of that flag in the corner.
Come on down, carry him over the shoulder.
There's he.
Trouble for Gary Ringrose.
He's out of the line out. Stop. He's out of the line out.
Keep going. Jimmy. Line out's on.
Island's line out. Five out.
Again, shortened numbers to secure possession.
James Ryan is accurate. Gibson Park moves it away.
Here comes Cailan Dorris.
25 year old.
Island set up.
Again. Use it now.
No, it's not. It's not.
Great Barrier Island in New Zealand.
And that one charged down.
He was onside the whole time. Thank you, Jimmy.
It's a big obstacle, isn't it, when you're trying to box out of there.
Portman OK for two, he's offside, but just about right side of the line.
Two minutes.
He's a real nuisance at the line-up time as well. He's giving it a bit.
Inaccuracy. Headline-out time for Island.
Could be very costly in this game.
This is the last attack for South Africa.
That angle. Krill's coming on there. It's really nice.
Go, please.
And the slight of hands from Marnie Le Boc.
That's the one that left Gary Ringrose feeling a little bit rusty.
Tried to put the big shot on Damian Di Alendi.
Not easy to do. OK, 13 green.
Sub. HIA.
In fact, Ringrose is going off for an HIA.
Tried to hit Di Alendi who's 106kg or so.
In the mould of Jean de Villiers, you might say, who's sat behind us here in the Coventry box.
Not a bad replacement from Robbie Henshaw there as well for Gary Ringrose.
Same message, timing.
We also have Bryna Disco, the great Irish legend that's here as well. Didn't bring his boots, he said.
Still a rugby World Cup record holder with the Irish side.
We've never got past the quarter finals, in fact.
I wouldn't believe that team to fall with the Irish side.
Robbie Henshaw coming in and he'll need all 70 caps experience.
Now 71 to defend this scrum.
To clap feeds for South Africa. They're up 3-0. 21 minutes gone.
Di Alendi goes upfield.
Daniel Di Alendi within 3 metres. South Africa on the verge of scoring.
He just stepped the toy stump and the ball's been pitched as well. That is excellent from Ireland.
South Africa scrum taken back. South Africa scrum.
No, it's been ripped by Green 11 and it's gone back into end goal.
At the moment, Daniel Di Alendi is taking out Ireland players one by one.
Honeylebock pre-calling that. I'm pretty sure he was saying you come back against the angle.
He almost pre-called the step, running into Johnny Sex and he put a good shoulder contact.
But it's come off second best.
James Lowe in there again doing a bit of back row work.
Maybe save the score.
You know what will happen.
Real worrying times for Johnny Sex and the captain of Ireland.
One of the most decorated players in the world.
He's for Frankie World Cup.
Okay, South Africa, time to go back on please. Ireland, time to go back on please.
Well, from the ball's line, this game is being played at a brilliant pace.
A great tempo.
A bit of a loose.
I'll say use it.
French legend.
No, no. It's taken back and then gone by Green.
I've heard you, I've heard you, Bongi.
Let's go, there's the Marcus in the middle.
Other legends in the house, Gough, Rory McIlroy from Ireland.
Michael Flatley, the celebrated Irish dancer is here as well.
Let's get back, let's get back.
See the way Marnie Labarque has just got his eyes widened at this area of the park.
When he knows he's getting the chance to create something.
Just at his fast pace, energising presence in this South African back line.
And he's got Villamse behind him here.
Goal!
Fine!
Six!
The Scrim box options, both sides.
The clack.
Short ball.
Jesse Kille very close.
Khaleesi loses it.
Ireland have it.
They're celebrating.
No, the ball is over.
The way they've repelled the Spring box, but it's not out.
Villamse.
Big step off his left, gets rid of one.
Does the full back for South Africa.
Visa.
Skips Mostad, goes to Steven Kitzhoff.
The one they call the angry plum.
Khaleesi takes, goes low.
Bounces out of a couple.
And a spill has come in there as well.
Please don't run into him.
I did not see him move.
This is the set piece.
Kille again.
Piercing through the middle.
What a tackle from Bandi Aki.
Chops him down.
Eyes on, gets low, takes the legs.
That is fabulous.
From both centres.
The ball is in.
For all money that was going to be a score.
Here's the turnover.
Just a little knock on in there.
James O'Spire up and why not.
The Ireland defence keeping them out.
Just about at the moment.
The timing is much better, Ireland.
Good patience.
That's the call.
One, two, three.
Coach.
Fine.
Six.
Last side.
Full noise.
Here it's Dr. France.
Sexton, whoops and wide.
K9 hold.
Kicked downfield by Hugo Keenan, the former 7th International.
Ireland work their way up the field.
Jimmy, control that mark.
We need to have good depth of this line out.
That's nifty.
Yeah, it is now.
We must have good space.
The South African back thrusters starting back to cover the kick.
But as the Ireland attackers in the back shift it.
Ireland.
The back three of South Africa have to come up, which then leaves that backfield space.
I actually think Hugo Keenan is so skillful, he probably would have wanted that to roll into the 22.
By his own standards.
He's been so impressive, really making that 15 jersey his own.
South Africa.
Solid with Khaleesi.
Sataku.
No, your hands.
No.
Thank you.
Clack.
Monty LeBoc goes to the sky.
Kurt Lee Aronson comes down.
Oh, what a contest that is.
Aronson wins it.
Another International 7th player lining it up here at the rugby field.
Lying it up here at the rugby World Cup.
Low thought about a kick and then the dunny and he's been had by Villamsa.
Ireland under pressure in their 22.
Josh Vanderfleet with a head-gear is there as well.
World Rugby Player of the Year in 2022.
Sexton just telling his forwards and backs where to go.
No, take a step.
Five, five, four.
Jamison Gibson Park.
Use it, nine.
No, you're still off.
Take a step behind the foot.
Etzebeth gets close, puts under pressure.
On the ground, knocked on by South Africa.
First forward in the year.
That's his 14.
Almost peel how nerve-racking that must be for Gibson Park trying to box.
Kick under that pressure.
And Etzebeth.
Kugelkeen potentially...
...laying Ironson in the air there.
That's pressure.
That causes Gibson Park to have to put thumbs off.
Different trajectory on his kicks.
He's got to almost go straight up in the air, which is why the ball dropped only about 10 metres ahead of where the rock was.
But Iris Chase is able to get up and make a mess of it.
Yes, so electric to see Kugelkeen Ironson.
12 tries in 12 games.
And Brad, did you mention Kugelkeen?
He's been 10 tries on the score for his country.
Cross the Olympic Games coming here next year to France at this very stadium.
Sevens will be played here.
Inside, start to France.
What an occasion.
Now we're going to restart with the scrum.
Ollumbo.
You want me to stop there?
We'll watch him on.
He'll be here watching the Sevens in the Olympics next year, no doubt.
He's going to be absolutely rocking.
He's going to be kicking off the Olympics.
Feet under you.
That's the message.
Feet under.
Next year.
His feet need to come under.
Your elbow needs to come up.
That's the message, okay?
Tidbit for you guys.
Willy LaRue is not in the 22 today.
The 23 today, I should say.
But he is running the water for South Africa.
A couple of experienced water carriers out there.
It's Keith Earl's, I think, down there as well running water for Ireland.
So a couple of useful, wise old heads.
Guys, we need to run the water on both teams.
Let's go, let's sit please.
We've been waiting too long.
Let's hit the scrum.
We've got the ball.
Nearly half an hour play.
3-0.
South African lead.
Ireland.
Typically low affair.
Only once in 117 years of this fixture.
As the team produced more than 50 points.
It was back in 2016.
6.
32-26.
So they have the 1-0-1.
Their last time.
They've beaten the Irish.
Gives them a pull-up.
Rolls it backwards.
Aki again.
Bursts through the line.
Bundy Aki.
Look at him go over the halfway line.
Aki is a sensation in this game.
Into the 22 for Ireland.
Gives them a little bit of a break.
Gibson Park.
Saw a bunch of watchers.
He's flying up on the right-hand side.
The side to take contact.
Numbers to the left.
Porter.
For Ireland.
Can they capitalise on their break by Bundy Aki?
He carries again.
Delayed ball.
You know, a manny is there.
Much better from this Irish side.
A second carry again from Andrew Porter.
Debut in 2017.
Sexton.
Crunched as he gives the inside ball to James Lowe.
Porter for the third time.
The hits keep coming.
Gibson Park.
Shifts it to the right.
As Ireland.
Trying to make some progress here in the 22.
Sexton.
Just that wall of white jerseys.
With Dutoy again.
Behind the back wall.
Trying to unlock.
Josh Vanderfleet.
Sexton.
Over the top he goes.
Bundy Aki yet again.
Beautiful ball to Lowe on the inside.
Needs help.
There's mustards all over him.
And a bindage for the Irish side.
Porter.
Nice dummy from the front.
But the field is open.
From Leicester.
A free play here for the Irish side.
With advantage.
Gibson Park.
Still got the penalty advantage.
Across they'll go.
The cross kick.
From Henshaw.
And Ireland will come back.
No clear release.
You're always in contact with the tackler.
Goes to ground.
No clear release.
So even if he stays on his feet as the tackle assist there.
Throwing the guy to ground.
He has to release.
Before he can get on the ball.
Bundy Aki.
How about that for a carry.
Down the middle.
I thought he was going to go all the way.
Showed a clean set of heels.
The South African defence got back in numbers.
And quickly so they could get off the line.
And start putting their typical shots in.
There were some brilliant tackles in there.
Franz Malhauver upending Andrew Porter.
Amongst many others.
We knew it was going to be a tight affair.
We've only got three points on the scoreboard so far.
Really off the five.
You get a look at the penalty there.
You can see he went all.
Never released the tackle player.
Before he then got on the ball.
Penalty all day.
Good spot from Ben Aki.
Very quick.
There's some good news for Ireland.
Gary Ringrose has passed his HIA.
And will return to the field shortly.
Thank you.
Will return to the field shortly.
That is great news for the Irish side.
They can't love that they kick for the corner.
Because here comes Callaghan now to the front.
Van der Vleer peels around.
Etzebeth hasn't.
Van de Aki.
The most dangerous runner tonight.
Still the Irish wave comes.
At South Africa.
Gibson Park to the right.
Forwards quickly regathering themselves for the next wave.
Peter O'Mahony.
Gibson Park looks both ways.
Again it's Van der Vleer.
Ireland inching their way closer to the Springbok trial line.
Beautiful play.
Sexton throws a dummy.
He gets so close to Johnny Sexton.
No, there it is.
Heads behind.
To the right.
No, the number's there.
Ireland will score.
And they put it down.
Mack Hanson.
Rooks one in for the Irish.
And the crowd erupts.
It's not the France.
Well that's a beautiful bit of play.
Johnny Sexton gets so close.
The scramble from South Africa.
And it goes wide.
Into the hands of the mustachioed Mack Hanson.
Who gets over for Ireland's first score.
Seven points.
If Sexton can pop this one over.
What a moment for Mack Hanson.
Born and bred in Canberra, Australia.
He played super rugby for the Brumbies.
Was actually convinced to come playing or go play in Ireland.
By iconic coach Andy Friend.
Qualifies for Ireland through his Irish born mother.
And he has another try on the big stage.
He's head of the head of this game.
These type of games, it's probably everything you dream of growing up.
Well, he might have to pitch himself.
Okay, thank you.
So sit up, we're just going to keep working.
Johnny Sexton.
From the right hand side.
I think we've got the right pitchers at scrum.
Gave it in 2009 in Dublin for his country.
Four, six nations titles.
Too many other titles to list right now.
He lines up the extra two.
Does Sexton.
It's straight through the middle.
It's Ireland's seventh.
South Africa's three.
And the flags are flying at 35 minutes.
It's a fifth pass to James Lowe.
Across the face of the defenders.
It cut out about three defenders that pass.
James Lowe just holding his feet.
Good hands. The catch and pass.
It felt like they earned that score.
It's a brilliant attack.
Really nice from the guys in the emerald green.
Going for the attacking line-ups as well.
It's paid full value.
So there's seven points.
Khaleesi has it for South Africa.
And Yolendi puts a kick over the top.
A one bounce.
And just like that, the spring box.
Putting on the pressure against Ireland.
Well, we've seen some bullish touches from VLND with ball in hand.
That was a delicate one.
Lovely little touch over the top.
I don't mind that, you know.
You've got Gertrude Arnst out there.
He'll chase anything and he's quick.
Ronan Callaghan.
To the middle.
Uncontested.
Gibson Park.
Ireland running upfield now.
Doris.
Penalty on the Ireland.
This will help them get down the field.
Fabulous carry from Doris.
It was Dutoy who was lying on the wrong side.
That's what can happen if you get the dominant carries.
So you get through the contact like that.
You can often leave tacklers stranded on the wrong side and they're liable to get penalized.
The Irish forwards on a 52% on their gain line success so far in this tournament coming into this game.
It's all about gain line success.
What a joy to have Bandiaki in the centers.
What a joy to be watching him.
Lovely little change of pace on the whip there.
One of the standout performers of this World Cup so far, Bandiaki.
What a venue for this cliffhanger.
Ireland in the 15th match.
Wind streak currently.
Sexton.
There's Aki again.
Flies into the line.
Doris loops around.
Gets a good ball and a good tackle in from Khaleesi.
Gibson Park changes direction.
Under flair.
Aki again this time.
Dielendi's there.
Two of the bulkier inside centers in World Cup.
Use it!
Okay, no.
So powerful.
Down now.
Javison Gibson Park.
And the place is kind of married.
It's come off the under change.
It's a good ball, thank you.
On Tonga.
Ardenseur.
Let's go backwards.
And David Villimsa is there.
The fullback to tidy up for South Africa.
First receiver.
Javan Etzebet.
Takes in a couple Irish players.
Monnie LeBoc on the left boot down the field.
Trans for a counter here.
Keenan does really well.
There's a fullback.
So he's upended.
Ringrose again.
Tackle!
Etzebet has him.
Such a ferocious battle at the breakdown.
No lift.
Big ball over the top.
James Lowe puts a kick through.
And this one will go out the back door.
Options.
See ya!
He mentioned it during that passage down the battle of the breakdown.
Drum roll 22.
Who's this gum?
It's been so good already.
So many strats in the jackal.
Which means that everyone technically and in terms of their urgency has got to be so good in attack as well.
Such a great contest.
This is what Keenan gives you.
The roaming runner.
Great work.
Really good, that's what I want.
You're watching the best players in the world here tonight.
Tell me, please.
Another get-as-pull.
He crosses over.
A little pull that includes France, New Zealand, Italy, Uruguay and Namibia.
Quarter-finals will take place here.
October 14th and 15th.
Coach!
Fine!
Six!
Seven!
Overboard!
South Africa.
Here comes Odense.
Behind the back.
And the bock.
Close and wide.
To Cheswin Colby.
He spins out.
Good tackle on him.
Score to try in the Rugby World Cup final.
In Japan last year.
The clap.
And that breakdown has been won by Ireland.
And the crowd will let you know that.
Well, case in point.
That's Jasper Wieser on the carry.
Yeah, I know exactly what you mean.
I saw the same picture.
He's had a sick seat, can't believe it.
Yeah, I'm watching it.
He's not an easy man to take down by any stretch of the imagination.
And yet, he got shot there.
Van der Vleer ended up sneaking in on the pill and robbing it.
Guys, is it the final ten?
Timekeeper?
Well, there he is.
Gets underneath.
But just before that was a brilliant display of tackling.
The back row just working together so nicely.
Steven!
It's pretty similar to Johnny Sexton's reaction in back play.
You can just see exactly what it means to Ireland's leaders.
Peter O'Malley, the back row.
And the back row.
And I'm sure you know exactly what it means to Ireland's leaders.
Peter O'Malley gave them a stirring pump-up before the game.
They are here to play today.
They really are.
And so far, the scoreboard shows that as well.
Vandee Aki, again goes in that middle channel.
Behind the backpull.
To Van der Vleer.
Ireland.
Back to the right hand side they go.
Porter is there.
Jasper Wieser.
hot. Sexton quick hands.
Tucked through long the Oxford Bull is there.
James Ryan catches forward.
For Ireland but Peter Stepter Tour has it.
Oh difficult pass for Khaleesi to take and almost.
Ireland coming through here and that is the first 40 minutes gone.
They're in Saint Denis north of Paris. It's the full b battle at the 2023 Rugby
World Cup. We knew it'd be close and it is the half time score.
Sees Ireland lead South Africa 7-3 from a packed start to France.
Last time Ireland played South Africa both countries scored two tries
each in the second half. The difference being a single penalty by Johnny Sexton.
Tonight it's start to France it's 7-3. Ireland
lead South Africa. Mack Hanson on the board for this Irish side. A big second
40 awaits us, Metri. Well we knew it was going to be close.
Previous meetings limited to Gap of six at max and the crowd here stand to their
feet. The balance in the crowd slide tipped
towards the Irish perhaps.
There's the South African legend. Familiar face.
We see him around the world the 7th circuit. Brian Havana.
One of the best to have done it out there on the ding-a-ling.
Record try scorer for South Africa. He watches on.
Bongi Mbanambi gears up for our second half.
Ringrose is good. He's back on his feet. Mustard.
Big imposing South African forwards. This Irish side
stacked with talented players. Sexton for their leader.
All good to see you. Andy Farrell looks on from Ireland.
You're watching the second half between Ireland and South Africa. From starting
start to France at the 2023 Rugby World Cup. Ireland on the left lead.
7-3 against South Africa. Bandiaki with a take.
Welcome to the thrilling rugby matchup.
Here comes Bissa for South Africa straight away.
So what? Pinori? A quick pinch.
Mustard. Pinori. To the line for the spring box.
And hold on.
Fours on the wrong side. A kick the ball coming out.
It's a bet. Again in trouble. Four whites.
Yeah I saw that in the ruck. He was on the wrong side.
The ball coming out. Comes out on your side.
We saw that penalised in the first half. The tackle line on the wrong side.
I think he probably is a good call from the referee or from his assistant.
It did disrupt that ruckball for Ireland.
Even Etzebeth came from a hell of a long way to make that first tackle.
He started on their own 10 meet line so that he could hit.
Just watching. Halfway running.
He's got a different ball. Just if we're going to take it quick.
So he's running at full tilt and he was the first to arrive to make the hit on Bundy Aki but then
slightly earlier than that. Okay let's start with good spaces.
Half and half. There he is lying on the wrong side.
See disrupting the Ireland ruck.
It's a bet. His ideal holiday isn't to the beaches of Greece but to the gym.
Here's coach Jafnina but looks on.
Gala head to the back. That's a great line up from Ireland.
Aki throws a short ball to his centre partner Ringrose.
And then Gibson-Pock puts one over the top.
It's a very good kick from the Irish number nine.
And it's South Africa that are capped in their 22.
Let's go please.
No changes to either side at half time so the South African bomb sport.
They're lying in wait.
It's never a ball. Confirmed it doesn't already out.
The suggestion was Peter Marny saying that hit Faf on his nose before it went out.
I think it might have done you know. Looked like it did catch him.
Maybe it was just a lock of hair.
That's bound to get in the way. The fuf the clack.
Mustard takes as the captain Sear Colisi goes upfield.
South African player here of 2021.
Captain South Africa to a series win of the British and Irish line.
Some of these players were playing against South Africa.
Hanson throws it to his fullback Keenan.
Cuts back in nicely. They link well and then he runs it to his own player.
Was Porter. That won't count as a tackle.
But Ireland still with possession playing on Peter O'Manning.
Sexton.
Oh that is a nice kick yet again.
Two in a row from the Irish halfbacks.
And he's saying it's touched.
So he wants a piece of this line out.
Whether they get it or not.
That's threaded that like a noodle down the touchline.
There's not really much on there. Look at the space he's aiming for there.
He's putting on an absolute sixpence so that bounces out.
Okay you got to stay out as we see.
They don't have one.
65 caps for South Africa interference close by in the lineup.
Ireland getting involved now against South Africa's attack.
We've got to offset Africa through.
Fives the call.
It's never your fault.
O'Manning getting up in front of Esabeth on that occasion.
No easy task.
Fighting fire with fire at line out time.
A massive opportunity for the Irish here.
Mossad returns the favour.
Peter steps it to a hazard four South Africa.
Never on the ball just the body.
No.
For the contest we've seen from the big men.
Okay use it.
Hold here.
Foster Clack plays alongside Jesse Creel in Japan.
Downtown is the kick to the halfway line pinpoint from South Africa.
This side of the half Jimmy.
Yeah go work.
It's an absolute master class in line out jump here at the moment.
The way the lifters are getting the speed with which those jumps are getting the eggs.
The lifters are throwing them getting right close together so they're getting the jumper
to the maximum height.
Get that those six line outs lost for Ireland.
Callaghan improves his stats.
He's through the middle.
On the flip.
Aki comes in down to the halfway line for the Irish side.
Kallera again takes on Kicsoff.
Khaleesi comes in.
Hands the pill stays with the ball.
The men in green.
Use it.
Sex them to the right hand side he lets his forwards attack a bit more.
Penalty South Africa.
He's well out of the way.
Holding on.
Five.
We've got some changes coming for South Africa.
RG Snimon's coming on so too is Quagga Smith and so is Jean Klein who has previously played
at international level for Ireland so this is going to be a very interesting experience
for him coming up against his old nation.
Three members of the bomb squad about to take the field here and there's Khaleesi getting over it.
Well he just hesitated a little bit on that one because he wasn't sure if he was legal
but there was nothing illegal about this.
Visa getting his legs nice and wide to allow himself to get low over that rock.
There's the light you mentioned.
Fafner Clack will line up this penalty attempt.
Third most capped.
Serapin scum off of all time behind the late Uus on the best asian
and Fareed Dupriya the rugby world cup winner.
From inside he's off.
Fafner Clack.
He's hit the upright.
It's come bouncing back and flying up there with Cheslin Colby force on Africa.
Somehow the spring box haven't.
Kille goes to the right.
Umber Nubby's there.
This may work out better for the spring box if they do score a try.
Jasper Visser crunches forward.
The Clack finds Ezeved who's picked up.
That is a highlight reel for social media.
Here the net's a bit.
Has been thrown out of the party.
Damian.
Time is a monster boot from the Clack.
Subs.
Four, five and eight.
Bounce back absolute chaos.
But how about this?
The big tree uprooted.
And it's going to be his last play of the match because he's coming off.
He's going to be angry.
He'll be very angry about that.
But the replacements are on.
You mentioned that earlier.
Oxencher is also coming on as well.
That's four replacements on the bench.
Jean Klein.
Erichir Sneyman.
Wocker Smith as well.
There he goes.
It's a bit.
The Viking they call him.
Erichir Sneyman plays his rugby monster.
A new prop.
Nice and square.
Good.
He's been lethal.
Defense.
He's off loading.
Tight head.
Feet underneath.
He's had an injury.
OJ Sneyman since 2019 but made an impressive impact on this World Cup already.
There's Wocker Smith.
I love watching him play the game.
An all-rounder.
He might seem slot in a few different positions today.
The Olympian Kofi Smith.
And Steven Kitzhoff goes off the field.
Now seven months to make two for Sabaev again.
Five for Ireland.
Big jump from the spring box.
Ireland pick it up the back.
They hit the deck.
And South Africa reward it with a penalty.
Five out.
There it is.
Number 12.
Sealing hands on the ground.
Andy Akir puts his hands up to seal it off.
We're gonna go again.
It's scrum time.
The South African engine room.
Fight out.
Timing.
Full force.
The island pack on roller skates there.
What a hit.
What a shove.
They're substitutes with South Africa doing the business.
Go.
Fine.
Six.
It's a sport that means so much.
For these two countries.
Reset.
Down far side.
We're down the far side.
We're gonna move it over here.
Very good.
Okay.
Keep that up.
Same message.
We've got to keep the height to the side.
The both of you.
150 firsts watching the scrums and being in them.
Ches and Colby right here in front of us in the far touch line.
But I think the action initially at least is gonna be up front.
For the spring box.
Crouch.
Fine.
Six.
Elbow up.
Vantage.
Leasing.
Clapsing elbow.
Vantage for South Africa with four of their bomb squad members on the field.
The Elendi beautiful ball.
On the outside.
South Africa will power over.
Cheslin Colby with the try.
Forget load shedding.
He's electric 24-7.
Cheslin Colby.
What we saw.
We hoped it would come to him eventually.
And it was Marnie LeBart that delivered the goods.
I'm happy with that.
The pass was good.
Cheslin Colby the Olympian.
He's magic in open space.
And there was plenty of it down in this touch line.
The only easier run in to have.
Please go back.
Thank you.
He dots down.
It's a statement score for the spring box after those two scrums where they absolutely
pushed Ireland back towards their own try line.
And you called it the wood from Colby just lurking on this left hand touch line.
So Africa have the lead now eight seven.
Referee Benno Keith.
Sorry, I just lost you.
Just checking something.
Yeah.
Thank you.
All good.
Shot clock back on please.
Here's the call for Benno Keith.
Marnie LeBart lines this one up.
URC record point scoring triasis in recent times for the Stormers from Cape Town.
Thank you.
Be just to me after this.
LeBart taking his time.
The clock ticks five seconds to take the kick.
Just pulls it to the left hand side.
But so now we go on front eight seven thanks to this try from Chesman Colby.
We can restart.
Well we just saw out of picture there it was Mack Hanson.
Taken out of the ball a little bit with the running lines but Tafka won't mind.
Some really big changes for both sides.
Marco van Staten's come on for the skipper Sia Khaleesi
while Ian Henderson and Dan Sheehan have both come on for Ireland.
Thanks man that's a lot of changes indeed.
As Ireland look to run it back with their number eight.
Kalan Doris studying psychology at University College Dublin.
Sexta taking back the glass.
Well fielded in the end.
Give him space 10 meters.
Pull back.
Hold.
Sia Khaleesi will look from the sideline now after being replaced.
Inside.
Feels kind of early to make that change.
Sexta.
Again to the heavens with that kick his full back chases.
Hugo Keenan is there against Villamsa.
And it stays with this African side.
Thok Declak tries to dig in.
Finds his fly off under pressure.
Creel has it.
Jesse Creel cuts in does the outside center.
Declak to Oxencheck.
Behind the back he goes.
Laboc finds Villamsa with a beautiful step.
No.
Damien Villamsa.
With some fancy footwork for South Africa.
Keep watching maybe.
Great presence of mind to let that one go.
Creel on the charge.
And there's Villamsa.
Fancy footwork indeed.
Steps out of it.
That is beautiful.
Such poise for a big man Damien Villamsa.
Good take.
Ian Henderson the replacement.
And a play out turns it in beautifully.
Dan Sheenan his Rugby World Cup debut.
Hasn't played for Ireland since.
They can't use it.
He's put in the warm up game against England.
But he's on the post.
But he's on the park.
On this mammoth stage in this mammoth game.
Charge down is there from Anfield-Snamon.
Advantage.
Low with a kick.
Offside play.
Offside.
Despite being as tall as the upper tower.
On purpose.
Sorry I didn't see that.
Offside guys.
Coming.
Perhaps Ireland may cover those changes.
Dan Sheenan, Ian Henderson.
Jemison.
It's a ball still.
I doubt that's on.
Don't dummy.
Get that line out.
Okay.
Might go the other way.
Yeah.
I worked on that occasion.
They came away with it.
Someone's still in someone's hand.
But I'm seeing it.
Sorry.
We've got the penalty here.
Stents now.
Sexton might just want to
steer this.
Control this a little bit in Ireland's favour.
Feels like as so often the case
with the Springboks.
And they make those changes.
Always dials the momentum in their favour.
Everyone's side on that.
Charge down round by the rock.
That guy make the catch.
Hats off to him.
I think you did.
Brilliant for the skill.
From this wonderful crowd.
To the front.
B.I. Manning.
Here come Ireland now.
Aki releases.
Sexton.
An intricate move.
Brings in low.
That beats one in short space.
Former basketball player.
Now rugby star.
Here comes Doris again.
The 25 year old carries well for Ireland.
Good counter.
And then a counter there.
Pocha Smith getting heavily involved.
For South Africa.
He's so versatile.
He's the MacGyver of rugby.
Can solve any issue.
Ken Pocha.
Good.
A bit of an accuracy from Ireland.
With the breakdown.
This was the set piece.
Play with the wrap around.
The little inside ball.
But South Africa pretty wise to it.
James Lowe making a few metres.
There's a carry for the back of this.
Doris where the post contact meters.
Then they were inaccurate.
They're still at the breakdown.
Big counter up coming in for South Africa.
You really feel now.
They've got the fire underneath them.
One point the difference on the scoreboard.
Plenty of time to go.
Thank goodness because I've enjoyed this Alan.
First off shot by.
And the same continues here.
This is Paul V.
Number one and two side in the world.
Happens to collide here.
Penalty to Ireland.
What a scrub.
From those forwards.
Careful.
Guys.
Tight head fully overextended.
Tight head fully overextended collapsing.
You heard from referee.
And I keep saying the tight head.
Overextending.
Now Herbert.
Looks like he did go down there.
Too long.
With his body shape.
Just got a little pressure there from.
Andrew Porter.
The crowd hushes.
And as Johnny Sexton.
World rugby player of the year.
A few years ago.
Lines up a potential lead for his country.
Sexton is a smooth operator.
And Ireland go back in the lead.
10-8.
As we approach the hour mark.
Alley Johnny Sexton indeed.
No lights needed.
From the Ireland coaching box.
You might as well have a coach out there.
Run around the tension.
The 38 year old.
So consistent.
So sharp.
He's used to winning.
Six Nations championships with Ireland.
But boy he'd love a World Cup.
You wonder is this a precursor for what's to come for Ireland.
Yeah unbelievable stat.
They have never got out of the quarterfinals at a rugby World Cup.
Nice take from the Irish side.
Can this be there yet?
2019 Japan.
The lost two to zero.
48 points to 14.
Gibson Park.
Has to pick quickly and scoot.
First the scum off.
Okay.
That better continue.
That's a conch is here guys.
You're fine.
In close quarters.
Use it.
Pundiaki.
No no.
He relieves it as Ian Henderson has a go.
He's third rugby World Cup.
Pretty experienced he brings.
Captain of the 78.
Use it.
Nine.
Timing.
Gibson Park.
He's putting everyone on.
To Villamsa.
Damian Villamsa.
Takes well and drives upfield.
For the spring box.
Buff the clock.
Throws a dummy.
They've got numbers wide.
No!
Hand off.
He just left the tweet.
Turning around the back was John Clay.
Going against his
teammates currently.
Again he carries hard.
What a story.
Playing both for Ireland and for that rigger.
In his career.
Kurt Lee Aronson.
With a lot of traffic in front of him.
Monty Lobach.
Finds.
Villamsa.
It's been left behind by Dielendi.
And that's frustration for South Africa.
Time off.
Well there's his aerial skill.
And he's so good you don't expect.
Errors.
A little dummy.
A little pump.
Dielendi was about to come underneath I think on the cut line.
I think Villamsa's frustrated with himself.
The hesitation.
That got the Irish crowd on their feet here.
Let's start to France.
New promise.
This timing hot.
Another change for South Africa.
Trevor Enyakar.
He has come onto the field for France.
Malheurva.
Another forward.
Taking part.
Third Rugby World Cup.
With Racing 92.
He's tripping.
Enyakar.
That's me all in.
Coach.
Finds.
Sits.
Ireland's possession as they crowd.
Resit.
Carries on this brilliant atmosphere we've seen.
We did it in dummy guys.
Hold the weights.
It's tense for everyone lads.
Don't worry about that.
Time's up for the shoot.
Okay guys.
Hold it.
No because it went down there Tom.
Yeah.
You guys all doing to restart the game.
Okay, time's on. Reset.
What an interlude listening to Fields of Afton Rye ring out in this stadium.
Crowds!
Five!
Six!
Ten half!
And the spring blocks call one back.
They're staying straight. Pushing straight. Oh, they're not staying straight.
Wow, the combo of Porter and Furlong.
The props of the island scrum.
So, Warder just for the kicker, nine hours away.
Being demolished on this occasion. You can see it's power gets underneath.
How are we looking at it? Are we looking at a sit-up now?
Underneath the chest there, Furlong.
Driving him up and in.
Kick's supposed to be good with Pepe.
Rani Lubock, from South Africa, with his country watching.
Dressed in such brilliant colour.
The Rainbow Nation.
This to take back the lead.
Staying still.
The red number's getting very low as Marnie Lubock looks on.
Unsuccessful.
The question marks remain around the goal kicker.
South Africa's worst goal-kicking record at this World Cup of any team.
Coming into this, just ten out of eighteen attempts.
And, unfortunately, Marnie Lubock only 40% kicking coming into this.
Questions mark remain.
Most of the changes coming from both sides. Finlay Bealham, Ryan Baird and Robbie Henshaw have all come onto the field.
O Marnie and Rick Rose both coming off the island.
While for South Africa, Dionne Furi has come onto the field.
Furlong Mbongi, Mbong Nabi.
Some big changes on both sides.
He can finish off strongly. Here comes Kocha Smith.
Loves eating green millies. He's not scared, he's Smith.
First touch for Dionne Furi.
He can be the oldest test debutant in South African history.
When his first cap was nearly 36 years of age and South Africa have a penalty.
At the halfway line.
Okay guys, 16 green was offside, 16.
Razir Azen's barking orders.
Down the microphone, down the walkie talkie, I should say to the touch line.
And we saw the traffic light again.
You've got to wonder.
A look on Andrew Porter's face going into that collision with Faka Smith.
The grimace, the determination.
Perfect.
The clerk's going to need more determination to steer this one between the uprights.
And boy, this team could do with it now.
The 31 year old.
Bangs it downfield.
And misses.
That's two different attempts from South Africa.
Keeps Ireland in the lead 10-8.
Substitution for Ireland.
And that's a change of scrum halves for Ireland.
Jamison Park, Gibson Park coming off the field.
The very experienced Conor Murray is coming off.
119 total caps for Murray. He's on the field now.
Here comes Faka Smith yet again.
To the right comes Vellumsa, the electric Damian Vellumsa.
Such a threat on attack.
Jean Klein carries now.
Born in Krugerstorp near Johannesburg.
Dielendi cut down at the halfway line.
Big rough ball for Fafnuklaagdau.
Vellumsa to the sky.
Lowe's there for Ireland, misses it.
That's a large hookup.
They're in their way.
Knock on.
Massively in the balance this game, isn't it?
Vellumsa's had a pretty all court game today.
We've seen him running into contact.
We've seen him stepping around it.
On that occasion he felt boot to boot.
Referee Gunnar Kiek nearly taking out Faka Smith.
It'll probably take more than a swinging arm to put Smith down.
Everyone square, moving forward.
Players like Smith allow him to do the 7-1 split on the bench.
He's got an outstanding skill set honed in the game of sevens.
He can carry, he can pass, he can do high balls.
Coach!
Five!
Six!
Sevens to fifteens.
Okay!
So every game, three time World Cup champions.
We trail now.
You have great work, great work.
The only champion to lose a cool game.
Happened in 2019 against New Zealand.
They lost early in the stages.
Carried in from Oxn-Chek.
The plays are jumping for the Sharks.
Good turn over.
Pitch to Swat.
The topside in the world.
They're led to do things like that.
A good carry from Oxn-Chek.
Backed up by Trevor.
Neer-Khani.
Time's up, let's go please.
We're good, okay we're good.
Time back on.
Getting in there.
Trying to make the difference for his team.
Charging that one down and deflecting it out for this line-up.
Arlham will throw in just outside the 22.
An error that's been problematic in this game.
And these are important moments now.
Dan Sheehan.
He was well nominated for World Rugby breakthrough player of the year in 2022.
22-22.
Akis there.
Inside their half.
Taking back.
Holden-Frons.
James Lowe.
Down the throat of Damian Villainsa.
Will he kick or will he run?
Throws the big left footed step.
Pass there from Markovan-Staden.
So they're working their way upfield.
Playing.
Lovock does well.
And here comes Arshia.
The Viking.
Sailing towards the 22.
So they're with numbers on the right hand side.
Lovock.
Creel.
Peter Steffert-Detoy.
Loses possession.
And it's a good tackle as well.
In from Konamari.
Do we not have a knock on or a touch by Isidabrega?
Well it looked like you knocked that on in the tackle.
Guys, South Africa ball.
South Africa ball was touched by Greenhand.
A bit of crap by lots of things.
Been late.
BOM also getting a look over.
Touched by Greenhand in the tackle.
Timo confirmed it.
Great hands from Lovock.
And a great look by the team.
And a great line from Snimon.
The big, striding second row.
And I think Detoy was just trying to lift it.
To his winger outside him is Aronson.
It's party time at the Rugby World Cup.
Ok, we're going to restart. Let's go please.
It's party time in the stands. It's a little bit more tense from the pitch.
Going into the ten minutes to go Mark.
It's so important now these players.
Coming into it was a lot made of this game.
I spanked the Irish management beforehand.
And they were saying yes there is.
But the consequences are less than they will be in the future.
In this competition.
So hopefully the players are allowed to feel the freedom and play.
With two points difference on the scoreboard.
One versus two.
This is going to be tense.
And it's about their ability to stay in the moment.
Stay processed. Stay composed.
Finally the pool currently.
Ten points to nine over Sarabaga as well.
The take.
For the Springbok.
Sean Klein. Nearly 140 matches for Munster.
Going against
Prenz.
In this Rugby World Cup pool game.
Advantage for the Springboks.
They're inside the 22.
Basta Klack pushing a few bodies away.
Banda Flea comes in.
Here comes Cocker Smith.
He's hit hard.
No, no. Over here.
It's the Ireland player.
Ireland comes around the side. Changes bond.
Side entry.
No, it was the same ball the whole time.
I don't know if it was
Tyburn initially with the infringement.
Around the side in the mall.
It's one ball.
And we might see another one
rolling. There he is.
Initially it looked like he came through the middle
which would have been fine.
I actually thought he pulled out perhaps under the referee's
instruction but penalised.
South Africa's chance
would tend to go.
They're five metres up.
Dionne Farik.
Not accurate.
One strike.
Well Ireland line-up coach Paul O'Connor
was asked before this whether they thought the introduction
of Dionne Farik would be
a weakness. And he kind of played it down.
Farik.
Is it back row flow?
Also plays it.
Transferred and
gives him that
variety.
Plenty of life experience coming in at 36 but
not a huge amount of game experience
at this level.
28 caps coming on for his ninth today.
Pressure in these
moments. Starting to boil.
It knew it would be an issue when
Malcolm Marks was injured.
No longer take
part with
the South African side of this World Cup.
Coach!
A chance for them to clear their lines.
Six!
Sigh of relief perhaps.
Big forward pack
piling in Ireland.
They're able to kick towards the touchline
using James Lowe.
That is a stunning kick from the Irish winger.
That is huge.
That was absolute giant nudge.
Huge change coming for Ireland here.
Johnny Sexton is coming off the field.
Of course he is a fan favourite.
He is a legend of Irish rugby.
He's a legend of Irish rugby.
He's been the heart and soul of this team
all night. He's going to come off
for the last eight minutes of this
absolute nail-biter Jack Crowley.
He's going. His replacement.
Sexton leaves his country with a lead.
Can they hold on to that?
Here comes South Africa up the middle.
Van Staden
gets a beautiful ball
from Kurt Lee Arnser
who had that break for the Springboks.
Attempts to finish her in for
beautiful ball back to
Coffa Smith from Ergis Neymar.
And here comes to Clark.
Labaugh. Unchet.
Steams upfield
for South Africa.
Trevon Yacany.
With possession.
But to Clark.
Can't get it. Ireland parling.
Fousey.
And then it's been left behind.
Hoof downfield from Ireland.
A stunning steal.
And they drive back the Springboks.
Jesse Creel.
Beats one.
South Africa.
They've got turnover at the last break time.
May have lost it again.
Ireland on attack. Here they come.
Ball splits free to the left-hand side.
Another look for some magic.
Keenan.
The fullback.
Walk down inside the 22.
Here they go. Release.
Conor Murray.
With this crowd urging him on.
Good ball again. Jack Crowley on the field.
The cheers continue.
Ian Henderson. The oesterman.
Behind the back ball.
Just held on there from Hugo Keenan.
The Fox doing well.
Porter.
Takes a strong hit.
There's Robbie Henshaw.
Looks to attack.
Ireland looking at the options here.
Todd Byrne.
Carries well again.
With Munster. They go to the pocket.
Not a successful attempt.
But they needed to have a go.
Got a scum.
Taking back.
It's going to be a five-year scum because he's charged down.
Been touched in the air.
Scum did.
There it is. Touched here.
Good work to charge it down.
They countered through.
Creel.
Scragged and caught.
And invited Ireland to counteract.
Another change for Ireland.
Andrew Porter coming off the field.
He's been instrumental today in that set piece.
Such has been the physicality of this game.
I think it's a well deserved break for him.
It's been the thick of it.
He's on the park.
Kovac-Rynup as well.
Great shot there at the RSI.
We're talking about how important it is to compose yourselves in these moments.
We're just over five to play.
They're there in a huddle.
Breathing in unison.
And South Africa have made the final change of their bench.
Stand-alone back.
Kovac-Rynup is on to the field.
Back to Klerk coming off.
Klerk is going to be on the field at some times.
He's said the only back.
Fan favourite.
Three years at Northampton Saints before he moved to France.
The second quickest in rugby world cup history.
Behind the one he set in 2019 against Canada.
It's a close one.
Can Arliff put this game away?
Five minutes to play.
There leads South Africa 10-8.
Come up.
Time's off.
Straight down.
Don't use your head on the shoulder.
It's your ball.
Let's reset please.
Time will go when we're ready.
It's tense. It's head in hands time.
You can barely watch.
Two points on the scoreboard.
Five minutes to play.
Island setting up camp at the scrum.
Five metres off.
It's an African line.
The experience of Conor Murray to put into this scrum.
Coach!
Fine!
Here we go.
As the world watches.
Kill the island.
Unstable.
You can hear the roar.
Shot called.
On the line please.
Mac Hansen just came up to this near side to fire the crowd up.
I don't think they need it Mac.
They're all on their feet.
They're loving life.
The substitute front row for Island will be very very pleased to get one over on the box pack.
A massive moment in the game for Island.
Jack Crowley.
Pivotal roll for the Munster side winning the URC this year.
From close range.
The
make it a five point lead.
Crowley has his name in the books.
It's 13 points to rate.
Island leads South Africa.
With three minutes to play.
The game is over.
Colby looks to the sky.
Is that a hint of despair in this African eyes now.
Down the middle goes South Africa.
Nice lift from Island.
Can they close out this game?
No. Manu Lubok launches the counter. A flower's being had and there's a bunch of green jerseys
around there. No. Rana retains possession for South Africa. Villainsa. Magic needed.
From some of the playmakers, Cheslin Colby. Can't get free on this occasion to the halfway
line. Turnovers good. A pinch and another steal from Ireland. Unbelievable from Bandiakhi.
Turnovers good. Storming with ball in hand. And on the other side of the ball. Low again. Chips
this one. Who's put him on? Colby. He's on there. He's opposite number. 90 seconds left. South Africa's
chance with ball in hand. Big hit as well. Rana Khan's possession. Inche waits. There's a behind
the back. Lubok. By Jesse Creel to the halfway line. The tackles keep coming from Ireland.
Vantage, second man. Hands on. Pindy Avani's foreside outrigger. Villainsa almost got the
pass away in the tackle and ended eventually. Okay, you got two penalties. One penalty here for off feet. South Africa. Cheers.
One here, one over there. From the South African side. Off feet. They're not a group short of
belief. They said coming into this they love the pressure cooker. Wow. It's dolled right up now.
Marni Lubok. So much said about his kicking in this game. And his shots at goal have been questionable. He's missed a few.
Well that's a nice nudge. He's giving his back. And inviting Blackpool to play here.
The drama unfolding in front of us. And starts to frown. Final play. Ireland lead 13-8. Farid goes to Peter
Tewi. South Africa. Mauling towards the trial. And Yelendi's in there as well. Tyburn. The Irish defender on the side.
They've defended superbly. So they're going to try to dig us out. It's there. Has he come out?
Ireland have done it. The number one team in the world. Irish eyes are smiling tonight. They've taken one step closer to their rugby World Cup dream.
They've beaten the Springboks. It's been an extraordinary evening in Paris. There'll be tears. There'll be celebrations. 80,000 fans.
Millions around the world have witnessed one of the great battles in rugby World Cup history.